[Music]
all right shall welcome to the scott
horton show
i'm the director of the libertarian
institute editorial director
of antiwar.com author of the book fool's
aaron
time to end the war in afghanistan and
the brand new
enough already to underend the war on
terrorism
and i've recorded more than 5 500
interviews
since 2003 almost all on foreign policy
and all available for you at
scotthorton.org
you can sign up the podcast feed there
and the full interview archive is also
available
at scott horton youtube.com
all right you guys um you know how i'm
always telling you that
uh even though gareth porter wrote a
book called the cia insider's guide to
the iran crisis
from cia coup to the brink of war that
doesn't make garrett the cia
guy it's his co-author john kiriakou
the torture whistleblower who's the cia
officer and they co-wrote the book
together that's the thing of it and man
is it good too
now manufactured crisis by gareth porter
of course is
the book on iran's civilian nuclear
program
but this one is all about that and more
and the entire american policy
and updated through the trump years and
all that the cia
insider's guide to the iran crisis by
gareth porter and john kiriakou former
cia counterterrorism officer welcome
back to the show john how are you
thanks doing well thanks happy to be
back with you
well good i'm happy to talk to you again
and especially on this important topic
hardly anybody knows this name it hasn't
seemed to have caught on as a viral
cause celeb with anything or anything
like that maybe someone needs to tell
pamela anderson
um yeah that uh this guy daniel hale
is going to prison he's already in
prison
even though he hasn't been sentenced yet
um
poor daniel for telling the truth about
american atrocities especially in
afghanistan
and in pakistan i think um so go ahead
tell us the story and tell us why it is
that he's already in prison if he's
supposed to be out on bail right now
you got it so daniel hale
was an nsa contractor
who was involved in the drone program as
a targeting analyst
and he recognized very early on that the
drone program
was carrying out illegal strikes on
civilian targets
all over the place yemen afghanistan
somalia
all over and um
he went to the
intercept to jeremy scahill uh
and he he wasn't you know covert about
it he
he was pretty well out there to the
point where he even appeared in a
documentary with jeremy
and on a college campus to talk about
the drone program
he was immediately arrested and charged
with multiple counts
of espionage and um
and has been fighting it ever since so
you know daniel as you might expect
uh has been depressed very depressed
at the prospect of going to prison um
what makes it worse is that he's broke
and he's represented by uh federal
um public defenders
now the federal public defenders even in
the eastern district of virginia
are terrific they're cleared they're
experienced
but like any public defender they're
overworked and underpaid
and they have other cases to worry about
too so
the guy is just petrified at the
prospect of spending
a good chunk of the rest of his life in
prison
so i've been in close regular touch with
him
and here's what happened uh
earlier this month you know what i'm
going to back up to march 31st march
31st
he decided to do something that was very
unorthodox
on his lawyer's advice he decided to
plead guilty to a single count
of espionage which carries a maximum
sentence of 10 years
there are four other espionage charges
pending against him but his calculation
was
if i plead guilty to this one count
which essentially covers
everything that he did the other four
counts were just heaped on
he was hoping that or is hoping that the
judge takes pity on him
gives him a short sentence and dismisses
the other charges well
because he decided to take this plea on
his own
and not as part of a deal with
prosecutors the prosecutors
have refused to drop the other four
charges so instead of facing
under 10 years which is what he was
hoping he's still looking at 50 years in
prison
so in early may
um he and i got together and he was
telling me that he's he's very depressed
but he's committed to fighting this
thing he explained his reasoning behind
the plea deal
and said that his lawyers kept bandying
about
the number five five years you know
maybe a little bit less
and i said daniel five years is a steal
and there's a trick to doing this
i said if you've got a problem with
drugs or alcohol
you go into something called the rdap
program
the residential drug and alcohol program
that the bureau of prisons runs
you sit there every week for a year and
you watch
a dvd of the a e network show
intervention and they take
12 to 18 months off your sentence and
then with good behavior they take
another 15
off and then six months and a halfway
house next thing you know
you're out in two and a half years
well for whatever reason the court
appointed shrink
that they ordered him to to talk to
every week
decided you know what this guy's
depressed and
maybe he's suicidal just in case
i'm gonna have him locked up for his own
safety well
i can tell you from personal experience
he was not suicidal
now he is because he's in solitary
confinement
quote unquote for his own safety
and um and he's stuck there
he's not going to be sentenced until
july uh 13th
and then you know what's he going to get
is he going to get 5
10 50 we don't know
and so that's what he's most worried
about yeah you got to love the idea that
if somebody really is suicidal the way
we put them on suicide precautions
is to lock them in solitary ridiculous
ridiculous and to make matters worse
um even if he wasn't suicidal which he
isn't
because of covid these holding
facilities are
all uh uh locked down so
he would be in solitary confinement no
matter what well the united nations
has said that the u.s practice of
solitary confinement is a form of
torture
and we know that when people are
isolated in prisons
they become suicidal but then again
maybe that's the calculation maybe
that's what they were trying to do
yeah was to make him suicidal who knows
and anybody i mean if you just think
about this for a second
um you know people say sometimes
imagine being locked in a thing the size
of your bathroom
but everybody's got kind of a nice
bathroom porcelain thrown and
shower and right uh cushy thing on the
floor
you know uh the bath mat and all that
that's a bad analogy i like the one
about
a parking space imagine being locked
in something the size of a parking space
by yourself
for an indefinite period of time there
and that's a fate worse than death
i'd figure out a way to kill myself
immediately i'll tell you what
circumstance
pretty much scott i i don't know
immediately but if i if i knew i wasn't
getting out of there anytime soon
yes well guess i had my chance of being
alive and now it's over
i spent 10 days in solitary confinement
one time
and you know it was difficult but not
crazy because i knew it was gonna just
be ten days
um but what made it hard was
uh they took my glasses from me and i'm
blind without my glasses
so i couldn't read anything there was
literally
nothing to do 24 hours a day they would
let me out for one hour every day
to um take a shower and to
exercise otherwise what i decided to do
was to get 10 000 steps a day now
this this cell i was in was six feet by
16 feet
so like you say it's a parking space
and i would just walk in circles
all day long and you sleep on a steel
bunk with no mattress no pillow
so i had to like ball up a bath towel
just to use as a pillow but it would
make my back and hips hurt
so much laying on a steel slab that i
would get up three or four times a night
and just keep walking in circles
any more than 10 days yes you're going
to start going nuts
and then because you're locked down um
you know
breakfast is is a little bit of oatmeal
and maybe a
an apple and then lunch and dinner are
a baloney sandwich a bag of chips and a
and a little
half pint of kool-aid and that's it
every single
day yeah
you know i think it's pretty easy to uh
can see if anybody ever read the
encyclopedia
of serial killers or anything about the
worst sorts of true crime stuff
people who commit horrendous atrocities
against children something like that you
think
you know i don't care what happens to
them right but
there's a lot of people in prison who
aren't the worst of the worst like that
at all
and get sent to the hole for pretty much
anything and
in some states like in louisiana and i
was reading i think in michigan
you just keep people in there for years
at a time sometimes and
for the slightest thing and these are
people even if they're convicted of the
very worst crimes
that just means that the d.a prosecuted
them that doesn't mean they did anything
at all as far as i'm concerned
uh that's right you know unless there's
obvious open
public proof beyond a shadow of a doubt
i don't trust a d.a and a judge and a
jury to do the right thing
and so totally and really right like
even even
someone that you know beyond a shadow of
a doubt is guilty of the worst crimes
against helpless
innocent people then still it's wrong
it's obviously a huge mistake to empower
anyone to have the authority this
the supposed authority then to treat
them in this way
because you see how they abuse it and
probably who deserves to be in the hole
more than anybody else
the people who are throwing people in
the hole amen
so true anyway and this guy is an
american hero
this guy and that's the bottom line
that's the bottom line this guy
sacrificed everything that he has
in his life to make this important
information public remember
and i know that this is a mantra with me
and people are probably tired of hearing
it
but it is illegal to classify a crime
if something is a criminal uh
event right if the government is doing
something that is
that is criminal like killing civilians
in something is in a zone an area that
has not been declared a war zone
that is illegal and because it's illegal
it's illegal to classify the program
and so as far as i'm concerned the guy
hasn't committed a crime in the first
place
yeah oh and clearly they're killing
innocent people and the the way that
and this is everybody can read this at
the intercept
um the assassination uh no
the drone papers it's called at the
intercept and the book
it's the same thing in book form is
called the assassination complex
and i relied on his leaking uh
you know in my book fool's errand about
the war in afghanistan
and the way he talks about how they're
just blindly killing people based on
not even cell phone numbers but numbers
of people who
ever were associated with a cell phone
that ever called another cell phone that
ever called another cell phone this kind
of thing
and then whoever they kill they just
label them all
enemies killed in action unless it's
proven otherwise
which it never is because they don't go
to investigate how guilty they are
and so um but then they also admit
that they have this incredibly low score
on their so-called jackpots where they
actually kill the guy they're trying to
kill
presuming that their intelligence saying
that he's an
enemy is even correct at all and it's
infinitesimally small compared to the
amount of collateral damage so it's not
really the same as the full-scale
invasion of iraq or something like that
where a million people were killed
but still it's thousands and thousands
and thousands
and probably tens of thousands of
afghans certainly
thousands and thousands of pakistanis
and somalis and yemenis in the drone
wars of the obama years
yeah you're absolutely right and you
know there's no
media outrage outrage uh nobody's
marching in the streets
yeah aside from code pink and the answer
coalition maybe
uh but this is not an issue that the
american people have latched on to
if it weren't for daniel hale we
wouldn't even have any idea really that
it was going on hey you said he was
featured in a documentary which one was
that
yeah it's called um national bird oh
okay
yeah it's i haven't seen that in a long
time now but i'll have to go back and
look and he's he goes
so this goes to what you said too about
he was pretty open about this
and you know the intercept has gotten a
lot of people caught and i know this is
an entire sub-speciality of yours john
um you know matthew cole the guy that
got you busted works there
and he's the same guy that got reality
win or busted um
but so you know this has been lumped in
in the same way that jeremy scahill or
the intercept somehow failed this guy
daniel hale
but so i wanted to follow up on that do
you really think it's the case that this
guy just got himself caught he wasn't
being careful enough got himself
caught correct so it wasn't anything
that the interceptor scale did sloppily
or anything like that
no and believe me i i'm happy to be the
first one to point the finger at the
intercept
but uh no that that's not what happened
in this case
he daniel decided that he was going to
go public and be
public about the drone program right
they didn't blow his identity
and guys you have to see national bird
everybody
it's so important and i don't know how
to find it online but i'm sure it's at
one of these things you know what
there's there's at least a trailer on
youtube
and i see here you can actually rent it
on youtube and on amazon
oh great uh yeah it's a it's an
absolutely terrific
documentary award-winning documentary
yeah
yeah it's really something else and you
know it
addresses the issues of ptsd and what
psychiatrists are now calling moral
injury right and those are two really
important
themes that have run through this cases
hey wait so let me tee that up for you a
little bit
oh come on a bunch of cowards hiding in
a trailer in nevada
murdering people hiding on the other
side of the
planet from the people they're killing
they have ptsd like they're
the infantry on the ground come on john
kiriyaku
you know you'd be surprised people act
like tough guys
and they're really not tough guys
they're they're human beings
so they spend all day killing people
like they're playing a video game
and then they go home to their families
and they act like everything is is
normal
i i was giving a speech at a at a
college in saint paul minnesota a few
years back
and a guy came up to me after the speech
and said that he had been a drone
operator
and that there was there was an event
that
had sort of pushed him into activism
he said that he was sitting there with
his his little joystick
and uh and his screen in nevada his boss
was at mcdill air force base in tampa
and they were both looking at their
screens and they identified what they
thought was the enemy
and uh the boss said fire and the guy
said
i can't fire there's a child there and
the boss said that's not a child it's a
goat
and he said it's not a goat i'm looking
at it it's a child and the guy
says i'm ordering you to fire and he
said i can't fire if there's a child
there
and the guy threatened to uh
to court-martial him and he said i'm not
gonna fire and he didn't fire and it
was a child and so he was
given a general discharged and pushed
out of the military but he said
you know we kill people all day long
every day
i have to be able to convince myself in
my own mind
that i'm only killing bad people i can't
just kill a child and pretend it didn't
happen
pretend that it was a goat and you see
this kind of thing all the time there's
a lot of footage in national bird
about where they've got audio of the
drone operators talking to each other
saying go ahead and fire no i think i
see a kid
ah it's not a kid no i think it's an
infant i think the woman's holding an
infant
oh are we supposed to shoot women too
well she is with the bad guy
you know these kinds of conversations
yeah where everything is black and white
it's all very stark
and then they end up firing and just
killing everybody
right and you know and then what is that
one of their comments too was
you know if you're flying uh an f-16 or
something like that and f
uh uh whatever the hell and dropping a
bomb on somebody you don't even really
know if you hit your target till you get
home
or you know you don't know much about it
right but when you're a drone pilot
you're sitting there hovering around
following these people around sometimes
for weeks
and you see their life you know who they
are where they work you see them
with their friends you see them with
their family and you
start even though it's all from a bird's
eye point of view you start to kind of
you know understand that their humanity
and fill in the gaps with your own
imagination about who they must be
and and what it is that and then now you
kill them
and so yeah you're hiding behind the
entire diameter of the earth
i said circumference earlier i meant
diameter but uh so you're not in danger
but still it's the moral injury it's not
the um
it's not the uh mortal fear it's
the guilt for looking back at those
people that you killed
and then in fact like even on the
children thing like obviously we want to
rule you don't kill children but then
that sort of de facto means that any
adult is fair game
you know if they do jumping jacks or you
know carry a bag of something over their
shoulder that's the signature of a
terrorist
and now you kill them will that be
murder in any other circumstance in the
world
in that murder and these drone operators
are very clear too that that any male
over
the age of 12 is a target is a
legitimate target
because any male over the age of 12 can
pick up an ak-47 and shoot an american
soldier
so it doesn't matter in many cases if
there are children there
they're perfectly happy to kill the
children too you know
you see a lot of wait a minute wait stop
for a second stop for a second
just to be clear here we're talking with
former cia counterterrorism official
john kiriakou and you're telling me the
rule is 12
years old yeah yes
and and in national bird you'll hear
these drone operators talking about it
like
well is the target old enough oh he
looks like he's older than 12. he can
pick up a gun
and then they just fire
can pick up a gun yes not that they have
the gun
but that they could pick up a gun that
makes them a legitimate target
see and this isn't this is that anything
is that any different than the gestapo
rounding up all the people that they
want to murder in the center of town and
just machine gunning them all to death
yeah you're you're absolutely right when
i was at the cia i worked for a guy
who um was in a very very senior
position
an agency-wide leadership position and
he had authority over
the kill list and so
he only lasted in the job about six
weeks because
they would call him in the middle of the
night and say um you know we've got the
guy in our sights the drones right on
top of him request permission of fire
and he would say well you know let's
think about this is his wife with
him are his kids with him uh are we sure
that it's the guy
are you sure you're on the right you
know jeep or whatever
and then by the time he's made up his
mind the guy's gone
and they said look when when people are
asking you for permission to launch
that's just a formality you're supposed
to say launch
and he wasn't willing to do that and
they fired him
there was another guy i used to sit you
know 10 feet away from
and every day we'd say hey man how you
doing hey how was your weekend how's
your family what's new what's going on
and then i said to a colleague i said
you know he's such a nice guy but i
don't even really know what he does for
a living here i sit 10 feet away from
him
and my friend said john he works in the
special
activities division what do you think he
does here
and i thought oh crap yeah he's out
killing people every day
like he'll disappear for a week at a
time and come back hey buddy how you
doing
and i'm thinking now geez how many
people did you kill over the last week
good grief man yeah but it's all to keep
us safe
right okay you guys check it out the new
book is finally done
enough already time to end the war on
terrorism
it's available in paperback and kindle
also the audiobook is coming although
that might take a little while
for all those who participated in the
big fundraiser of 2019
i have the list and you will be getting
all your stuff as soon as my boxes of
wholesale copies arrive
thank you so much to everybody for your
support of the show
and of the libertarian institute and i
hope you like the book
hey guys scott horton here for
expanddesigns.com
harley abbott and his crew do an
outstanding job designing building and
maintaining my sides
and they'll do great work for you you
need a new website
go to expanddesigns.com scott and say
500 bucks hey guys check out listen and
think audio books
they're listeningthink.com and of course
on audible.com
and they feature my book fools aaron
time to end the war in afghanistan as
well as brand new out inside syria
by our friend reese ehrlich and a lot of
other great books
mostly by libertarians there reese might
be one exception
but essentially they're all libertarian
audio books and here's how you can get a
lifetime subscription
to listen and think audiobooks just
donate 100
to the scott horton show at
scotthorton.org
donate listen we're going to get back to
daniel hale in a second but
your job was grabbing the actual
co-conspirators in the 911 attack out
there in pakistan
in the early days of this thing so yes
on some level
and i read one of your books i forgot if
i read two
i got what biden's got nowadays kariakou
forgive me
um but uh so
obviously you're gonna defend some of
what you did there as absolutely
necessary
but then at what point you're telling me
the real terror war ended
and the bogus one began then that's a
great question
you know right after 9 11 when i was
sent out to pakistan to head counter
terrorism operations there
my orders were very simple my orders
were to
capture and send them to uh to
guantanamo
where they would wait for two three
weeks
before going on trial in the united
states in the federal districts of
boston new york and washington that was
the original plan
and when what when we made our first
captures i called headquarters and i
said
well we got these guys what do you want
me to do with them and they said
oh put them on a c-12 we're going to
send out a c-12
and send them to guantanamo and i said
guantanamo cuba
and they said yeah i said why in the
world would we send them to cuba
and they said we're just going to hold
them there for a couple of weeks until
we can
figure out which federal district court
to send them to for trial
and i said oh okay that's a great idea
so my job was to
was to take them alive put them on a
plane
and send them home for trial and that
actually never
happened guantanamo became
a permanent weigh station nobody went on
trial and i
recognized relatively early on that this
just wasn't going to work
i recognized it when we captured abzu
beta
march 22nd 2002 he was shot and wounded
and we sent him to a secret prison
and then began torturing him on august
1st 2002.
so it was clear to me then
that the system that we knew
and loved as americans that was
enshrined in the constitution
was not going to work these guys were
not going to get
the constitutional rights that that they
you know
deserved and of course they're still
being held down there
the people who are actually guilty are
still yet to be convicted of that crime
that's the ones who really deserve it
right like ramsey been all she been
colleague sheikh mohammed
exactly how many more of those guys are
really guilty john down there out of the
40 that are left at guantanamo
you know probably around a dozen
were were truly bad guys but then you
have people
like muhammad udlahi
from mauritania i've become friendly
with with
muhammad um you know this this poor son
of a gun
the reason why the cia grabbed him
was because he had a
cousin who was a low-level nobody in bin
laden's
circle and the cousin
had called him
on a cell phone to ask him to check in
on the cousin's dad because he heard
that his dad was sick
so he calls muhammad rude slali slahi
and says hey can you go
in the village and check on my dad i
heard he's not doing very well
and he's like sure i'll go check on your
dad and the agency grabs him
you got a phone call from a a known
cell phone near bin laden and the poor
guy's 14 years in guantanamo
well there were a lot of people like
that and a lot of people who had done
even less than that
who ended up in guantanamo man i
interviewed a air force colonel
who was representing you know was the
mandated attorney defense attorney
representing a guy
who was in there i guess this would have
been in 2014 or something like that so
he'd
done a good dozen years in there or more
and
they finally admitted the evidence
against him with salt and sugar
or the precursor chemical weapons you
know al-qaeda terrorism links that he
had
yeah see what they do like you said a
minute ago
scott that there are some bad people
down there khalid sheikh muhammad is a
bad guy
he has the blood of 3 000 americans on
his hands
but how do you put a guy on trial when
his confession
and most of the evidence you have
against him uh
you you collect it as a result of
torture you know what why don't they
just parachute him into the idlib
province to join forces
with abu mohammed al-jalani and his
friends there the moderate rebels
against assad
exactly he must be so jealous of jelani
right
that's not fair cia gives this guy a
billion dollars i'm languishing in
prison down here
right and and he's legitimately al-qaeda
oh yeah
um well and in fact i can't wait till
the
the full front line documentary comes
out but uh
you know he says oh yeah no we're not
really part of al qaeda anymore but
martin smith evidently did not say to
him oh yeah
we'll denounce i'm in al zawahiri right
now
and let's hear it you know yeah i didn't
hear it
that didn't come up anyway let's talk
about my man here
um 50 years so tell me
i i understand he was throwing himself
on the mercy of the court and the doj
bad call they prosecute him on the
espionage act
so his lawyer just could not get a deal
they just would not give him a deal so
he just decided to plead guilty anyway
and just
hope that somehow that would
you know change their mind a little bit
they would go easy and they're just not
so
he's essentially and and he's going to
be sentenced in what two months
yeah july 13th um the feds would not
budge off of 10 years
and daniel the last time i talked to him
he was so distraught
he just kept saying i can't do a decade
i can't do half a decade
i can't i can't get through it and i
kept telling him daniel
you're far tougher than you realize you
are
and then with rdap and good behavior and
house arrest and and
halfway house it's not going to be
a long period of time i said listen i
was in prison for like
a week and the acting boss of the banana
crime family asked me to take a walk
with him it was snowing
it was evening it was dark and we're
just walking in circles around the
outdoor basketball court and he said to
me
how much time do you have and i said 30
months and it feels like
30 years and he said let me give you
some advice
if someone asks you how long you have
you tell them you have five years
because if people find out that you have
a sentence that's so short
they're gonna kick your ass because
they're they're jealous
so tell people that you're here for five
years and then he says to me
two and a half years are you crazy he
said you can do that
standing on your head between good
behavior
and halfway house you're gonna be out in
a year and a half maybe two
and i ended up going home after 23
months
he's like you could do the time on the
surface of the moon for 23 months
and he was right you know it was just
depression clouding my
my judgment and i tried to convey this
to daniel too
it seems like a lifetime but
it's not you know i was facing a maximum
of 45 years but realistically 12 to 18
years had i gone to trial
and one of my lawyers said he told me to
take the deal
for two and a half years and he said
this can be a blip in your life or it
can be the defining event of your life
make it the blip and i know that's what
daniel's trying to do
but he's still so close to the issue
that he just can't get past
the idea of five to ten years now with
that
he's really lucky to have a friend in
you though john to give him all this
advice
from you know your first person point of
view there
oh thank you that means a lot to me i
i'm i i
i'm so worried about the guy i'm so
worried about his mental health i'm
afraid he's gonna do something out of
desperation
and i'm trying to get him to just relax
but how do you do that in solitary
confinement well you know i think you
told me before too that
the italian mobsters all really liked
you because they're really patriotic and
they like
cia oh you're seeing all right you can
you know be friends with us
does that work if you're nsa too yes
i'll tell you who it doesn't work for is
fbi i
freaking hate the fbi as much as i do
and that was one of the reasons we were
able to bond like we did
in fact i'm still in touch with all
these guys we're meeting up again
in a couple of weeks in atlantic city
maybe i shouldn't even say that but
but you know the they're they're
honorable
guys they're they're criminals in their
own little worlds
but honor and duty and patriotism mean
something to these guys
yeah all right well let's change the
subject now
um daniel ellsberg has
not exactly recently leaked a document
he
he posted on the internet two three
years ago when his
book on nuclear weapons came out the
doomsday machine yeah
and i think from what i read in well
it's charlie savage so you never know
but
in charlie savage's uh you know
rendition of the story in the new york
times um
he posted a footnote in the book that
said hey listen you can go and look at
this document
and it's got things that are not in the
redacted version
but nobody really noticed that or picked
up on that i don't remember that
but then apparently a historian at the
national security archive at george
washington university did notice it
and went and found it and then somehow
i forget exactly the cause and effect
where uh
this came back to ellsberg's attention
and ellsberg decided to promote it and
give it to savage
uh to publish in the new york times
and it's a document describing the
debate over whether to nuke
china over taiwan in 1958
yeah right ellsberg also
said to charlie savage you tell the
department of justice
i said indict me oh and people if
people are wondering he stole this
document back he liberated this document
back when he liberated the pentagon
papers
yeah uh this was one of the few that he
was able to hang on to on the nuclear
weapons topic
he apparently lost most of him he says
but he's 90 years old now john
yeah he celebrated his 90th birthday a
few weeks back i'll tell you what i
i'm i'm almost 57 years old so i'm sort
of beyond the age of having heroes
but dan ellsberg is my hero he's sort of
the
the godfather to all national security
whistleblowers
but i am so honored to be able to call
him a friend
uh i i i see he listens to this show too
he tells
you're kidding me walking on my
treadmill listening to your show scott
and that's just the highlight of
my life oh that's wonderful yeah dan is
a wonderful
patriot hi dan uh
he's a patriot and you know
even after all these years all these
decades now
to stand up to the to the justice
department and to the national security
apparatus
like he is doing is inspirational yeah
and by the way we're going to have him
on the show next week he's busy writing
an
op-ed for the new york times right now
oh fantastic
but then uh so we're going to have him
on the show next week to talk about this
and he is essentially
i mean the plan this to be very clear
for everybody here john
the uh he is trying to get indicted
and prosecuted on what could be a life
sentence
charge for leaking this top secret
information about nuclear war although
it is out of date it's still highly
classified
and he's daring them to indict him and
prosecute him
and convict him for espionage the same
way they did to you
the same way they're doing to daniel
hale right now the same way they did to
thomas drake and so many other great
whistleblowers
of this century so far and then
he wants to take it to the supreme court
and he's confident that the first
amendment will protect him
and that the supreme court in the case
of ellsberg versus these pigs
will finally strike down this practice
once and for
all you know he and i had a conversation
back in
2013 or 14 about
appealing an espionage act conviction to
the supreme court in order to try to
have it
ruled unconstitutional which i i believe
it is it
and my lawyers did too it's
unconstitutionally broad
and unconstitutionally vague it's it was
written in 1917
to combat german saboteurs and it
doesn't even mention the words
classified information because the
classification system hadn't been
invented
when it was written it refers only to
national defense information
and then doesn't define what national
defense information
is so he said that that the problem
with appealing it is that there were
only two people with standing
who could appeal it one was chelsea
manning
and the other was jeffrey sterling
because they had gone to trial
and were convicted at trial but then you
know chelsea said
she just couldn't do it like she just
didn't have it in her to go all the way
to the supreme court
jeffrey sterling was excited about it
for a short while and then said
the whole process was so depressing he
just wanted to get past it
and so once he lost at the appellate
level in the
in the fourth circuit in richmond that
was the end of it
so here's dan you know in the twilight
of his of his years
trying to write a historical wrong
and using himself as
as bait for the justice department the
guy guy's a giant
yeah the guy's a giant and i know that
history is going to be very kind
to him yeah well everybody already loves
them and everybody already knows that
he's the guy that ended the vietnam war
yeah and he's on top of all that he's
just a really great guy
yeah he is yes you know he's a guy that
you want to have a beer with
or have dinner with just a really great
human being
yeah you know i've known him for like a
dozen years or more now oh
no i've known since what 04 03 or i
guess before
oh five maybe was the first time i
talked to him uh so quite a while now
but i've never met him in person yet
uh yeah he's one of these days i need to
go visit uh erica and the guys in san
francisco and uh
see if that means but before the feds
take him away
i better hurry uh now so is this going
to work is
is uh merrick garland going to take the
bait
and indict daniel ellsberg i i can't
imagine you know dan would have such a
strong defense because in the united
states we have a mandatory
declassification law
where unless um unless a document
contains
sources and methods where the source is
still alive
uh it has to be declassified after 30
years or you have to present a
compelling reason why it shouldn't be
declassified
i would argue and i think dan's
attorneys would argue
that um a document that dates to 1958
should have been declassified decades
ago
and uh and that prosecuting dan
for a document that's so old is you know
not justice
right i i can't imagine
i can't imagine they would go after him
like this i think
a trump uh justice department may have
done it
but i can't imagine that joe biden
would want to pick a fight this is the
obama team well
that's the thing it is the obama team
you're correct about that yeah
okay well i guess we'll see this time at
this time it doesn't include
john brennan and brennan was the driving
force back then and also obviously this
is an
ambush and they you know they don't want
to walk
right into it probably but yeah
then again the president shall see that
the law is enforced that's a big
show yeah well that's that's a good
point
yeah i don't know um but then we come
back to that idea of prosecutorial
discretion
all right well you know what i don't
want to see anything
bad happen to daniel ellsberg but you
know what i'd oblige him
if this is what he really wants you know
um wow listen so let's talk about the
document for a second because
one of the reasons that he decided to
make a big deal about it now
was because there's a question and
there's
and i have no idea what whose likelihood
and who measures this and how well
but the idea is that china might decide
to try to retake
taiwan by force sometime in the next
near-term future here
and then so what are we going to do
about it and in this document it becomes
clear that
well geez i mean if we need to use nukes
we use them
what's the point of view of all the
people in the military at the time
it was president eisenhower who said
actually we're not going to do that
but evidently and this is the way i
learned it as a kid too
that it was only because they were
afraid of what the russians would do
yes they thought that if they nuked
china then the soviet union would
nuke america and all our allies in
europe and so that was why they decided
not to do it
not because they gave a damn about nuke
in china or not
and yes to them it's just another bomb
it's bigger and
okay there's a bright flash and there's
this you know so-called taboo
against using it and crossing that
threshold but hey
rubicon's across all the time man
america's used nukes
against civilian cities before twice
and at the time it was perfectly
thinkable
according to these doc and in fact
everybody needs to read the doomsday
machine by daniel ellsberg
it's about exactly how thinkable the use
of nuclear weapons really is
and man it's this is really something
else
yeah this is this is crazy and
you know this is one of the points that
that dan makes
is that this this attitude this
this analytic viewpoint that nuclear war
is winnable uh lasted well into the
1980s
you know there were a lot of people on
the right
and certainly within the u.s military
who believed that
you could launch nuclear weapons and
you know have an end game and win
uh this was a different situation
because we were afraid of that soviet
response
but there this was a real debate inside
inside government and especially inside
the pentagon
that we could nuke china and win this
thing
yeah well and you know what yeah we
might lose a few cities
but that's acceptable yes right
yes and you know actually i guess
they think that they can shoot down
enough of
china's retaliatory capability they have
a couple of hundred nukes at least uh
what 300 or something
and uh the americans figure that don't
worry we can shoot down enough of the
incoming it'll be fine
we might lose a few cities like san
francisco and los angeles and denver and
houston and
but other than that though it'd be okay
crazy just crazy and you know it's funny
too
uh in the document that dan leaked
there was one uh general i think he was
an air force general who was the
commander for the pacific
who was specifically asking for
authorization for a
first use nuclear attack where he didn't
have to go back
to the white house or to the pentagon
for permission to launch
he wanted permission in advance to make
the decision
on his own to attack china
it's just insane to think about it yep
all right so and everybody can go read
that it's by charlie russian bounties
cia stenographer savage in the new york
times
there uh he is as i said in the book
he's the second or third
least worst reporter at the times you
gotta grade these things on a scale
uh no before you agree uh before i let
you go here i gotta let you say a word
about julian assange
yeah uh julian's dad and
and uh brother are coming to dc
soon uh they're in they're gonna be in
boston next week
dc the week after uh and this is after
having completed a speaking tour
around australia you know
what can you do besides shake your head
i i participated in a in a zoom call the
other day with a whole bunch of
of journalists it was chaired by rob
reiner of all people
and um uh there were there were three
night ritter journalists
uh who were on and
a friend of mine from veteran
intelligence professionals for sanity
asked the knight ritter uh guys why the
mainstream media especially people
involved in national security reporting
uh weren't showing any support for
julian assange when he was clearly
a journalist now when you say knight
ritter i mean knight ritter's been gone
for a while but i think
is that a euphemism for jonathan landay
and warren strobel
yeah i mean knight reuters is pretty
pretty well gone but yes they were both
on the call
and and in unison they said that
julian assange is not a journalist he's
an activist
and i was flabbergasted in that jonathan
landay what is the matter with him
damn you land i like him too but
uh these guys it was clear that they did
not want to talk about julian
so you know afterwards he's an activist
didn't you know
kiriakou it says in the first amendment
that you're not allowed to have an
opinion when you do
journalism like jonathan landay doesn't
have any opinions
about say for example how much he trusts
his cia sources
when they feed him a bunch of crap about
donald trump and vladimir putin for
example
those aren't opinions that's doing the
cia's work that's real journalism
you're absolutely right you are
absolutely right
julian assange is an activist and then
what's the s
what's the rest of that sentence so he
goes to solitary confinement
for doing journalism while
what does that even mean anyway an
activist that's a pretty malleable
territory confinement you know for for
what reason
he he won the case right the extradition
case it's being appealed right now
but he's he's still in solitary
confinement pending the appeal
despite the fact that the british courts
on three separate occasions have
upheld a lower court's refusal to
extradite prisoners to the united states
specifically for the reason that the
united states
uses long-term solitary confinement
so there's no way the justice department
is going to win this case in the british
appellate courts there's no way but then
the brits hold them in solitary
even though that's their objection to
sending them here
can you imagine can you imagine i was
talking to
stella morris the other day julian's
partner and the mother of his children
and she said that his his emotional
state is fragile
you know even the strongest person
breaks in solitary confinement
his health is bad because the guy has
not been exposed
to sunlight for something like nine
years
and uh the longer that he's in there the
worse it's going to be
man you know you think about it too
it's so obvious why there's no support
among the people i mean i understand
about a cia tool like savage or land a
but
for the people out in the country the
partisan population
of the country that swing you know left
or right on this
the other reasons for hating this guy
right he undermined bush
and the war and made the republicans
look horrible
when he put out the manning stuff and
then
he hurt the democrats and in essence
helped to get trump elected by
publishing
all of the podesta and dnc emails that
showed how they rigged the game
against bernie and actually for trump in
the primaries
because they thought he'd be the weakest
guy to beat in the general the pied
piper strategy all that in there
and um and so people have
something against him but you just turn
that around and go hey this guy's done
something that your side really
appreciated too right remember that time
he helped take down hillary clinton
remember that time he helped take down w
bush so
can't we agree on the positive aspect of
this
even if you're a partisan can't you find
enough to say like hey
this guy for god's sake and and for
anybody who's not a partisan
he told the truth about the wars in
afghanistan and iraq and what was going
on at guantanamo bay and all the state
department files
there's 30 000 news stories must have
come out of that stuff
and then he saved the world from hillary
clinton
exactly right he saved humanity from a
hillary clinton presidency that makes
him like one of the greatest heroes who
ever lived
and he stopped jeb bush at the same time
too come on
yes well he didn't really stop jeb bush
that was trump but anyway
bush also lost that year and it was
great not that i'm a big trump guy but
i'm
very much an anti-bush and clinton guy
and so i don't know it just seems to me
like
even if you're a partisan you ought to
be able to look with favor on assange
instead of just scorn
you know yeah it's publishing great
truth and you know what it isn't like
he's a traitor who's
you know like aldrich ames who's like
selling out the highest level american
agents who were all getting their
throats cut
out you know behind enemy lines or
something like that this is all
secret level not top secret but it's a
no it was the truth is what it was
it wasn't the kind of thing that got
sources and methods destroyed at all
you're exactly right exactly right
we should be celebrating the guy man
yeah
america's really messed up right now um
all right now listen you and your
article consortiumnews.com
saying hey people can write to daniel
hale and tell them how much you love
them and
how badly you need them to hang in there
so how does that happen
yeah the poor guy um right to daniel
hale
he he may not be able to write back to
you because he's only allowed to
purchase 10 stamps
a week uh they're real dicks about
about the uh the rules over there at the
federal lock-up in alexandria so it has
to be on plain white paper with no lines
it has to be in black ink and it can't
contain
any photographs he's desperate
for news he asked me specifically to
please please send news articles but
what you have to do
is cut them and paste them onto a white
piece of paper and delete the
photographs from them
so it's just the you know the the words
um but yeah he he said he would try to
write back
if he gets permission to buy extra
stamps
uh but he's he's lonely and he's
depressed
and he has no idea what's going on in
the world around him
man all right and then uh the address
here is
daniel e hale comma
william g truesdale looks like it sounds
t-r-u-e-s-d-a-l-e
adult detention center william g
truesdale adult detention center
2001 mill road
alexandria virginia 22314
one more time y'all daniel e hale
william g
truesdale adult detention center
2001 mill road alexandria virginia 22314
and let me add one more thing uh you can
you can get a whole bunch of additional
information
at standwithdanielhale.org oh great
yeah standwithdanielhale.org
all right listen thank you so much uh
for coming on the show and for writing
this great article and sticking up for
this guy the way you are john
thank you so much always good to talk to
you all right have a good week
appreciate it
the scott horton show anti-war radio can
be heard on kpfk
90.7 fm in la apsradio.com
antiwar.com scotthorton.org
and libertarianinstitute.org
you